Willard Eugene Hotchkiss Arbitration Awards and Papers 5238
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Willard Eugene Hotchkiss Arbitration Awards and Papers
1917-1946
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Hotchkiss, Willard Eugene
5238
2 cubic feet
2 linear ft.
Decisions, manuscripts (documents), speeches (documents).
The arbitration awards and papers of Willard Eugene Hotchkiss include speeches and writings, including some book reviews (1917-1940); also arbitration awards, chiefly for the Textile Workers' Union of America (1937-1945), and United Steelworkers of America (1939-1944).
2293765
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, October 31, 2012
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, February 22, 2017
Biographical / Historical
Dr. Willard Hotchkiss (Ph.D., economics, Cornell University, 1905; LLD., Northwestern University, 1927) was an educator and arbitrator. Professor Hotchkiss was a member of the faculties of Northwestern University (1905-1917, 1921-1925), the University of Minnesota (1917-1919), and the Carnegie Institute of Technology (1930-1944). He served as dean of the School of Commerce at Northwestern (1908-1917), dean of the Graduate School of Business at Stanford University (1925-1932), and director of the Division of Humanistic and Social Studies at Carnegie (1941-1944). Hotchkiss' business career included his work as executive director of the National Industrial Federation of Clothing Manufacturers (1920-1925), as president of the Armour Institute of Technology and lesser posts. Dr. Hotchkiss served the federal government as panel chairman of the War Labor Board (1943-1945) and as public member and chairman of the Enforcement Division of the National Wage Stabilization Board. Professor Hotchkiss was also an arbitrator and mediator, working largely in the textile and steel industries.
Scope and Contents
Hotchkiss' writings include, "History of the Shipbuilding Labor Adjustment Board, 1917-1919" (1921); "Industrial Relations in the Men's Clothing Industry" (1922), discussing reasons for formation of a national federation; "Collective Agreements in the Men's Clothing Industry" (1922), a discussion of the role of agreements, representation and arbitration in the men's clothing industry; "Industrial Relations Management" (1923), concerning ideas on human relations and personnel management; "Unemployment Agreements Between Members of the Chicago Industrial Federation of Clothing Manufacturers and the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America" (1923); "Extra Incentive Wage Plans in the Men's Clothing Industry in Chicago" (1925); "The Human Factor in Industry" (1926-1927); and "Arbitration -- an Analysis" (1939).
Addresses by Hotchkiss deal with the beginnings of constitutional government in the men's clothing industry (1921), stabilizing employment in the men's clothing industry in Chicago (1924), employee representation (1924), labor relations (1940), and miscellaneous subjects.
The arbitration awards (1937-1945) chiefly include the awards with agreements, briefs, petitions, minutes of arbitration proceedings, and letters. The awards are chiefly for the Textile Workers' Union of America vs. the American Viscose Corporation (1937-1945) for cases involving discipline, seniority, suspension, wages, schedules, and other miscellaneous issues. Additionally, there are a number of awards and supporting materials for the United Steelworkers of America (1939-1944) vs. various companies and corporations for cases involving wage rates and discharge. There also are a number of awards for cases involving the United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America, United Automobile Workers, Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America, Aluminum Workers of America, United Stone and Allied Products Workers of America, United Mine Workers of America, International Brotherhood of Boilermakers, Newspaper Printing Pressmen, International Typographical Union, and Federation of Glass, Ceramic and Silica Sand Workers of America.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Arbitration, Industrial -- United States -- Cases; Personnel management -- United States; Psychology, Industrial -- United States; Industrial arbitrators; Clothing workers; Iron and steel workers; Textile workers; Arbitration, Industrial -- Aluminum industry -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Automobile industry -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Boiler making industry -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Building trades -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Clothing industry -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Electric industries -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Glass manufacture -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Men's clothing industry -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Newspaper publishing -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Printing industry -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Shipbuilding industry -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Steel industry -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Stone industry -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Textile industry -- United States; Employees, Dismissal of -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Employment stabilization -- United States -- Addresses, essays, lectures; Hours of labor -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Industrial relations -- United States -- Addresses, essays, lectures; Labor discipline -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Seniority, Employee -- Law and legislation -- United States; Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- United States; Hotchkiss, Willard E. (Willard Eugene), 1874-1956.; Aluminum Workers of America; Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America; American Viscose Corporation; Baltimore Motor Coach Company; Federation of Glass, Ceramic and Silica Sand Workers of America; International Brotherhood of Boilermakers, Iron Ship Builders, Blacksmiths, Forgers, and Helpers; International Typographical Union of North America; International Union, United Automobile, Aircraft, and Agricultural Implement Workers of America; International Union, United Automobile Workers of America (A.F. of L.); Sun Shipbuilding and Dry Dock Company; Textile Workers Union of America; United Electrical, Radio, and Machine Workers of America; United Steelworkers of America; United Stone and Allied Products Workers of America; United Mine Workers of America
2293765
- Labor in the Inland Empire Lumber Territory memo, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Response to request of lumber operators following action taken in December 1917 at the request of the War Department, includes correspondence with lumber company executives
- The Bases of Industrial Stability, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  From Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science, Philadelphia, September 1920, Publication 1432, Governmental policy as discussed in the President's National Industrial Conference
- History of the Shipbuilding Labor Adjustment Board, 191T to 19195 co-author Henry R. Seager., 1921 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  U. S. Bureau of Labor Statistics Bulletin No. 283, May
- Men's Clothing Industry, Beginnings of Constitutional Government in, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Abstract of an address by Willard E. Hotchkiss before the Minnesota State Bar Association, July 26
- Industrial Relations in the Men's Clothing Industry, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  RE: Reasons for formation of National Federation, International Labour Review
- Book review of: Report on the Steel Strike of 1919., 1922 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Commission of Inquiry, Interchurch World Movement, Public Opinion and the Steel Strike of 1919, Supplementary reports to the Commission of Inquiry, Inter-church World Movement, The Three-Shift System in the Steel Industry by Horace B. Drury, (Bulletin of Taylor Society, February 1921) from the Journal of Political Economy, June 1922
- Collective Agreements in the Men's Clothing Industry, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  From Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science, Philadelphia, September, 1922, Publication No. 1658, Discussion of the role of agreements, representation and arbitration in the Men's clothing industry
- Industrial Relations Management, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Basic ideas on human relations and personnel management, Reprinted from the Harvard Business Review, July
- Unemployment Agreements between members of the Chicago Industrial Federation of Clothing Manufacturers and the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  October
- Management Leadership in Industrial Relations, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  From Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Sciences, Philadelphia, January 192k, Publication No. 1766, Discussion of the Report of the U. S. Coal Commission
- Plan for stabilizing employment in the Men's clothing industry in Chicago, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  From Seventh Annual Human Relations in Industry at Silver Bay, New York, August 29
- The High Points of a Conference on Employee Representation at Cleveland, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Nov. 13th-14th
- Closing remarks at a conference on Personnel Administration in College Curriculum, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Extra Incentive Wage Plans in the Men's Clothing Industry in Chicago, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  From American Management Association Production, Executives Series: No. 20
- The Human Factor in Industry, 1926-1927 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Reprint from the Commonwealth Review, Vols. VIII-IX, Nos. 4-1, Oct.-Jan., Speech at Semi-centennial of the University of Oregon
- Remarks on Bill S-2926 before the U. S. Senate Committee on Education and Labor, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  March 15th
- Arbitration - An Analysis, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  From Society for the Advancement of Management Journal. Vol. IV, No. 2, March 1939, p. 45
- Hypothetical Arbitration Case used at Pittsburgh Labor School, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Labor Relations - Yesterday, today and tomorrow, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  Outline of a talk before the Allegheny Foreman's Club, January 16
- Bethlehem Steel Company and United Steelworkers of America, Locals 1374 and 1639, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  Nov. 24th
- Bethlehem Steel Company and International Die Sinkers. (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Unemployment Agreement in the Chicago Men's Clothing Industry. Annals. (Box 1, Folder 22)
- San Francisco Building Industry, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Oct. 17th
- Mill Owners' Association of Philadelphia and United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Philadelphia District Council, April 25
- Agreement, American Viscose Corporation and Textile Workers Union of America, 1937-1938 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- General Motors vs. United Automobile Workers: Tab Barrel Case, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Feb. 3rd
- American Viscose Corporation and Textile Workers Organizing Committee, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Five Cases of Discharge and Suspension at Lewistown and Meadville, Decisions, April 11
- American Viscose Corporation and Textile Workers Organizing Committee, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  Cases of Louis Cohey, Marcus Hook, Pennsylvania, Sept. 28
- American Viscose Corporation and Textile Workers Organizing Committee, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  Case of James Gilmartin, Marcus Hook, Pennsylvania, Sept. 29
- American Viscose Corporation and Textile Workers Organizing Committee, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  Seniority Cases from Marcus Hook, Pennsylvania, October 8, 1938, February 16, 1939
- American Viscose Corporation and Textile Workers Organizing Committee, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  Cases of Francis Ferrari and Holiday and Vacation Make-up Work, Nitro, West Virginia. February 17, 1939
- American Viscose Corporation and Textile Workers Organizing Committee, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  Case of John Williams, Meadville, Pennsylvania, March 13, 1939
- American Viscose Corporation and Textile Workers Organizing Committee, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  Suspension Cases at Meadville, Pennsylvania, March 15, 1939
- American Viscose Corporation and Textile Workers Organizing Committee, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  Patrol System in Parkersburg, Lewistown and Marcus Hook Plants, March 23, 1939, July 11, 1939
- Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, Local 86 and Labor Standards Association of Pittsburgh. Adjustment of Wages in Department Store, Alterations Depts, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  April 20th
- American Viscose Corporation and Textile Workers Organizing Committee, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  Discharge of Floyd Rouschie, Lionel Rheinhardt, Robert Gilmore, and Gordon Bell, Meadville, Pennsylvania, July 11, 1939
- Steelworkers Organizing Committee and Oliver Iron and Steel Corporation: Case of Barthel Erbe, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  July 14th
- American Viscose Corporation and Textile Workers Organizing Committee, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  Pipefitters Helpers Seniority Cases in Meadville Plant, July 15, 1939
- Steelworkers Organizing Committee and Pittsburgh Steel Foundry Corporation, Emergency Wage Adjustment, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  July 19th
- American Viscose Corporation and Textile Workers Organizing Committee: Case of Edgar Staley, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  Meadville, Pennsylvania, July 15, 1939 provisional, August 26, 1939 final, December 6, 1939 supplemental incidents
- American Viscose Corporation and Textile Workers Organizing Committee, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  Cases of Mariam Sutley and Earl Krotzer, Meadville, Pennsylvania, December 6
- Pennsylvania Transformer Company and the United Electrical Radio and Machine Workers of America, Local 615, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  Article VIII - Adjustment of Grievances, Section 1 and Article X, Arbitration, Sections 1 and 2, December 18
- American Viscose Corporation and Textile Workers Organizing Committee, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  Seniority of Dialyzer Employees, Roanoke, Virginia, June 29, 1940
- American Steel Band Company and Steelworkers Organizing Committee, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  Wage Arbitration Case, July 6
- Aluminum Company of America. Aluminum Workers of America, Local #2, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  Case of Paul J. Pastrick, May 2
- Steelworkers Organizing Committee and Vanadium Corporation of America, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  Case of Andrew Campanucci, July 23
- American Viscose Corporation and Textile Workers Organizing Committee, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  Case of Charles Milam, October 10 (missing)
- Steelworkers Organizing Committee and Timken Roller Bearing Company, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  Case of Discharge of Five Employees at the Columbus Plant. November 1, 1941.
- Steelworkers Organizing Committee and J. & L Steel Corporation, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  Case of Carl Moore, February 10
- American Viscose Corporation and Textile Workers Organizing Committee, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  Case of the Second Class Welders, March 26
- National Tube Company and Steelworkers Organizing Committee, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  RE: Appropriate Number of Grievance Committeemen at the Ellwood Works of National Tube Company, March 26
- United Stone and Allied Products Workers of America and Blair Limestone Company, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  RE: B. G. Racey and Robert Michael, April 25
- Murray. Ohio Manufacturing. Company and International Union of United Automobile, Aircraft and Agricultural Implement Workers of America, Local 65, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  Monetary Issues, June 2
- United Steelworkers of America, the Washington Tin Plate Company, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  Wage Arbitration, June 2
- Reading Eagle Company and Reading Printing Pressmen and Assistants' Union, 160, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  Appeal from Decision of local Chairman, June 12
- Willys-Overland Motors, Inc. and Mechanics Educational Society of America, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  Wage Rates, July 15
- Carnegie-Illinois Steel Corporation and United Steelworkers of America, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  Shear Crew Case at Homestead Plant, August 12
- Parkersburg Iron and Steel Company and United Steelworkers of America, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  Wage Arbitration, August 12
- Neville Company of Pittsburgh and District 50, United Mine Workers of America, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  Wages and Union Security, August 19
- Philadelphia Transportation Company and P. R. T. Employees' Union, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  Case No. AR-3 before N. W. L. B., November 10
- Crucible Steel Company of America and United Steelworkers of America, 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  All Atha Works. Hearing September 3, 1942, decision, partial, November 13, 1942, General comment Supplementary findings, January 9, 1943, Communication to Messrs. Fench, Moselle, Schnitzer and Wisner, January 14, 1943, Memorandum on Case 125, March 17, 1943, Final decision April 9, 1943
- Marietta Manufacturing Company and International Brotherhood of Boilermakers, Iron Ship Builders of America, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  Case AR-139, November 18
- Pittsburgh Coal Company and United Mine Workers of America, Local 1787, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  Dispute involving Crescent No. 1 Mine, November 20
- Agreement. American Viscose Corporation and Textile Workers Union of America, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  Nov. 30th
- H. K. Porter Company and United Steelworkers of America, Local 1592, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  Wages - Cranemen, December 2
- Andrews Steel and United Steelworkers of America, Locals 22 and 1870, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  Vacation Pay Seniority, December 24
- National Supply Company, Spang Chalfant Division and United Steelworkers of America, Local 1244, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  Arbitration in Respect to Fourth Shift, January 2
- Pitcairn Company, Pittsburgh Valve and Fittings Division and United Steelworkers of America, Local 2276, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  Dispute over Discharge of Six Workers in Pitcairn Company's Mechanical Foundry, January 16
- American Viscose Corporation and Textile Workers Organizing Committee, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  1-2 Seniority in Yard and Viscose Plant, 3 Lunch Relief in Mercerizing Cellars, 5 Rate and Schedule on B-ll Machine, Lewistown, Pennsylvania, January 26
- New York Newspaper - Printing Pressmen's Union No. 2 and Publishers Association of New York City, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  Appeal from Decision of Local Chairman, February 22
- Aluminum Company of America and International Die Sinkers Conference, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  Case No. 882 - N. W. L. B. March 13
- Allegheny Ludlum Steel Corporation and United Steelworkers of America, Local No. 1196, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  Dispute at Brackenridge Plant (Pennsylvania), March 20
- United Steelworkers of America and John A. Roebling's Sons Company, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  Rate Case, March 23
- Bethlehem Steel Company and International Die Sinkers Conference, Lodge 50 Independent, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  Case No. 890. N. W. L. B. March 13
- Lukens Steel Company and United Steelworkers of America, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  April 17th
- Crucible Steel Company of America and United Steelworkers of America, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  LaBelle Plant Cases, April 19
- General Chemical Company and United Mine Workers of America, District 50, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  Wages and Shift Bonus, April 20
- Universal Cyclops Steel Company and United Steelworkers of America, Local 178, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  Discharge of James Jacobs, April 30
- American Viscose Corporation and Textile Workers Organizing Committee, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  W. N. Carter, Roanoke, May 13
- Irwin Foundry and Mine Car Company and United Steel-workers of America, Local 2452, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  Decision - Dissent of Labor Member of Panel, May 21
- Babcock and Wilcox Tube Company and United Steelworkers of America, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  Carlton and Mills Rate Case, June 2
- Clarksburg Publishing Company and typographical Union 372, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  Wages, June 30
- Mid-West Abrasive Company and United Steelworkers of America, Local 2292, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  Dispute on Vacations for Employees, August 11
- Pittsburgh Plate Glass Company and Federation of Glass, Ceramic and Silica Sand Workers of America, Local 25, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  Wage Arbitration, N. W. L. B. August 14
- Pittsburgh Steel Decisions, 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  Including Pilger Mill Case handled by American Arbitration Association, August 13, 1943 - Decision, Case 576, Preliminary statement No. 607, 611, September 17, 1943 - Decisions, nos. 607 and 611, September 16, 1943, Pilger Mill Decision, January 20, 1944, Reversal
- Worcester Publishing Company and Newspaper Printing Pressmen and Assistants' Union No. 29, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  Sept. 13th
- American Viscose Corporation and Textile Workers Union of America, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  48-hour Schedule, Spinning Room, Lewistown, October 26, B-ll Marchine - Marcus Hook, November 12
- Bethlehem Steel Company and United Steelworkers of America, Lebanon Plant, Local 1374 - Steelton Plant, Local 1639, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  Lebanon Plant, Grievances 1239 and 43, Steelton Plant, Grievance 777, November 24
- American Viscose Corporation and Textile Workers Union of America, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  Request for Adjustment re Relation Piece Rate and Work Load - Case Stripping and Wrapping, Marcus Hook, December 20
- American Viscose Corporation and Textile Workers Union of America, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  Request for Shift Premium, Reeling Research Lab, Marcus Hook, December 20
- American Viscose Corporation and Textile Workers Union of America. W. T. Snider Discharge Case, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  Dec. 28th
- General Machinery Corporation and United Auto, Aircraft, Agricultural Implement Workers, Local 955, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  Hamilton, Ohio, Grievances 1138 and 3381, January 27
- American Viscose Corporation and Textile Workers Union of America, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  Multi-Deck Spinning Step Rate Case, Front Royal, Case Suspended pending telegram from W. L. B. February 4
- American Viscose Corporation and Textile Workers Union of America, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  Case - Replacement of Males by Females, Front Royal, Settled at Front Royal Hearing February 4
- American Viscose Corporation and Textile Workers Union of America, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  Ash Handlers Case, Lewistown, Withdrawn March 20 (Letter from Mr. Krafft)
- American Viscose Corporation and Textile Workers Union of America, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 74)
  Plant, Fibro, Spinning Work Load Case, Front Royal, Case suspended March 20 (Letter from Mr. Krafft)
- J & L Steel Corporation and United Steelworkers of America, Aliquippa Works, 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 75)
  1. Case No. 4 - Seamless Case May 10, 2. Bessemer Converter Crane Operators March 20
- United Steelworkers of America, Local 1375 vs. Republic Steel Corporation, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  Train Crews in Open Hearth Transportation, May 10
- American Viscose Corporation and Textile Workers Union of America, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 77)
  Schedule for Daylight Engineers, Lewistown, Withdrawn May 13 (Letter from Mr. Cook) Process Piece Work Rate Case, Lewistown, Temporarily withdrawn May 13 (Letter from Mr. Cook)
- American Viscose Corporation and Textile Workers Union of America, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 78)
  Drill Press Rate Case, Lewistown Plant, May 19, Spindle Motor Winders, Lewistown, Withdrawn May 13 (Letter from Mr. Cook)
- American Viscose Corporation and Textile Workers Union of America, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 79)
  Leadburner Training Programs Case, Front Royal, Suspended Judgment, May 19